Guide to the Peter Orlovsky Papers
Rare Book and Manuscript Library Columbia University Libraries
Peter Orlovsky Papers
1954-1971.
Orlovsky, Peter, 1933-
.75 linear ft. (1 document box, 1 half-size document box)
Columbia University. Rare Book and Manuscript Library New York, NY. 10027
MS#0954
4079181
The papers of the poet, member of the Beat Generation, and Allen Ginsberg's lover. The collection is comprised primarily of correspondence with some sketches, photographs, and diary fragments.
History
Peter Orlovsky was born in 1933 to Oleg, a Russian immigrant who painted silk neckties and Katherine Orlovsky, an aspiring writer. He was born in Manhattan, on the Lower East Side, but grew up on Long Island in the town of Northport. The family was poor and both Oleg and Katherine were alcoholics and the Orlovsky's five children were often neglected and abused. The oldest son, Julius, went mad and had, eventually to be institutionalized, and both Peter and his younger brother Lafcadio struggled throughout their lives with substance abuse.
Peter, the second of the Orlovsky's five children left his mother's home at 17. He worked as an orderly in a mental hospital in Queens while taking night classes to complete the requirements for his high school diploma. In 1953 he was drafted into the Korean war where he served as a medic in a hospital in San Francisco.
In 1954, Orlovsky and moved in with painter Robert LaVigne acting both as the painter's model and his lover. Through LaVigne he met other writers and artists, most significantly Allen Ginsberg. Orlovsky and Ginsberg almost immediately became lovers and within months entered into a marriage that would last most of the remainder of their lives.
Ginsberg and Orlovsky lived together first in North Beach in California and later in New York City, but also traveled extensively throughout Europe and the Mediterranean as well as India and Pakistan. Though he lived and traveled all over the globe, Peter felt his responsibility to his brothers Julius and Lafcadio keenly, and his trips abroad were often abbreviated in order for him to care for one or both of them.
With Ginsberg's influence and encouragement, Orlovsky began writing poetry in 1957 while the two were living in Paris. He was first published in 1960 and continued to write throughout that decade, though this is also when his own drug use, particularly amphetamines, was at its worst.
In 1970 Orlovsky moved to the farm Allen Ginsberg purchased in Cherry Valley, New York to pursue organic farming and his writing. He joined the faculty of the Jack Kerouac School of Disembodied Poetics at the Naropa Institute in 1974 to teach the course "Poetry for Dumb Students" and remained a core member of the faculty for several years. He was awarded a $10,000 National Endowment for the Arts grant in 1979.
He is the author of several books of poetry including Dear Allen: Ship will land Jan 23, 58, Clean Asshole Poems & Smiling Vegetable Songs: Poems 1957-1977, Lepers Cry, and the volume Straight Hearts' Delight--Love Poems and Selected Letters, by Orlovsky and Allen Ginsberg as well as publishing poems in a number of periodicals. He was also featured in Robert Frank's documentary film Me and My Brother (1969), which explores Julius Orlovsky's mental illness.
Scope and Content
Correspondence of Orlovsky with Allen Ginsberg, William Burroughs, Gregory Corso, Herbert Huncke, Jack Kerouac, Michael McClure, Philip Whalen, and others. Also, manuscripts of Allen Ginsberg, Lafcadio Orlovsky, and Peter Orlovsky, including his extensive diary notes for 1954-1955.
Arrangement
This collection is arranged in II series.
Series I: Correspondence, 1957-1971
Series II: Drawings, Writings, Photographs, 1954-1958
Subjects
Ginsberg, Allen, 1926-1997.; Burroughs, William S., 1914-1997.; Corso, Gregory.; Huncke, Herbert.; Kerouac, Jack, 1922-1969.; McClure, Michael.; Orlovsky, Peter, 1933-; Whalen, Philip.; Orlovsky, Lafcadio.; Beat generation.; Bohemianism--United States.; American poetry--20th century.; American literature--20th century.; Diaries.; Authors.
Access Restrictions
This collection is located on-site.
This collection has no restrictions.
Acquisition
M-59 05625F
Related Material-- at Columbia
Allen Ginsberg Papers at the Rare Book & Manuscript Library
Selected Related Material-- at Other Repositories
Peter Orlovsky: An Inventory of His Papers at the Harry Ransom Humanities Research Center
- Series I: Correspondence, 1957-1971
  This series contains correspondence sent to Orlovsky, as well as some of his outbound correspondence. His incoming correspondence includes letters from members of his family and from friends such as Gregory Corso, Jack Kerouac, and Michael McClure. The bulk of the incoming correspondence is from Allen Ginsberg, sent while he was traveling through Europe and South America. Some of the Ginsberg correspondence includes poems or drawings along with the letter. There are also letters that Peter sent to friends and family, in particular to Janine Pommey. The correspondence series represents the bulk of the collection.
  - Corso, Gregory
    - to Peter Orlovsky, 1957-1960 (6 letters) (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - to Peter and Julius Orlovsky, 1969 August-October (2 postcards) (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Ginsberg, Allen
    - To Peter Orlovsky
      - 1957 (5 letters) (Box 1, Folder 3)
      - 1958 (14 letters) (Box 1, Folder 4)
        (includes poems “O Blake! Blake! Blake!” and “World! World! World!”)
      - 1960 January-May (20 letters) (Box 1, Folder 5)
      - 1960 May-July (10 letters) (Box 1, Folder 6)
      - 1961-1967 (11 letters) (Box 1, Folder 7)
      - 1968-1971, (10 Folders) (Box 1, Folder 8)
    - To Peter Orlovsky and Denise Filieu, 1971 April-August (6 letters) (Box 1, Folder 9)
    - To Lafcadio Orlovsky, 1960 March 16 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Ginsberg, Louis to Orlovsky, 1965 May 15 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Glassman, Joyce
    - To Orlovsky and Allen Ginsberg, 1957 October 28 (Box 1, Folder 12)
    - To Orlovsky, 1958 February 13 (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Huncke, Herbert to Orlovsky, 1960 February 28 (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Kerouac, Jack to Orlovsky, 1957, 1960 (6 letters) (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - McClure, Michael to Orlovksy, 1960 April 27 (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - Miles, Barry to Orlovsky, 1965 October 19 (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - Orlovsky, Katherine
    - To Peter Orlovsky and Allen Ginsberg, 1957 October 4 (Box 1, Folder 18)
    - To Peter Orlovsky, 1957-1959 (5 letters) (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - Orlovsky, Lafcadio
    - To Peter Orlovsky and Allen Ginsberg, 1957 (2 letters) (Box 1, Folder 20)
    - To Peter Orlovsky, 1958 January 8 (Box 1, Folder 21)
  - Orlovsky, Marie, To Peter Orlovksy, 1959 February 26 (Box 1, Folder 22)
  - Orlovsky, Peter
    - To Henry Schlachler, 1957 September 4 (Box 1, Folder 23)
    - To Katherine Orlovsky, 1957 December 31 (Box 1, Folder 24)
    - To Janine Pommey, 1961 March-October (10 letters and postcards) (Box 1, Folder 25)
  - Whalen, Philip to Peter Orlovsky, 1958 February 13 (Box 1, Folder 26)
- Series II: Drawings, Writings, and Photographs, 1954-1958
  This series contains sketches, dairy entries, and a small number of photographs created by Peter Orlovsky. The diary fragments are loose and many are undated.
  - Drawings
    - Miscellaneous Drawings (Box 2, Folder 1)
      (done mostly on paper napkins)
    - “My Father and his Leg in Our Room on the 3rd Floor,” 1958 July (Box 2, Folder 2)
    - [Sketch of Robert LaVigne], 1954 (Box 2, Folder 3)
    - [Portrait Sketch], unattributed, circa, 1956 (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Photographs (Box 2, Folder 5)
    (3 photos of Orlovksy and Allen Ginsberg shot by the Harold Chapman Studio, 1 photo booth frame with Gregory Corso, Allen Ginsberg, Paul Carroll, and Peter Orlovsky)
  - Diary Fragments and Notes, circa 1954 July-1956 January (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - “Restraint and Seclusion Order,” 1958 (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - Miscellaneous Envelopes (Box 2, Folder 8)